this episode is sponsored by indeed
prime indeed prime helps software
developers simplify their job search and
land their dream job candidates get
immediate exposure to the best tech
companies with just one simple
application - indeed product companies
on Prime's exclusive platform message
candidates with salary and equity up
front
the average software developer gets five
employer contacts and an average salary
offer of $125,000 indeed Prime's 100%
free for candidates no strings attached
and when you're hired indeed prime gives
you a two thousand dollar bonus to say
thanks for using prod but if you use the
SE radio link you'll get a five thousand
dollar bonus instead so sign up at
indeed.com / se radio
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se Radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer /
software welcome listeners to another
episode of soccer engineering radio
today I'm talking to Camille Forney
who until recently was CTO at Rent the
Runway where she led a team of over 60
engineers who were responsible for both
the customer-facing technology as well
as the custom logistic system prior to
that Camille served as a software
engineer in Microsoft and most recently
as a vice president at Goldman Sachs
where she dealt with RISC technology and
technology infrastructure
Camille is very well known with the tech
community speaking on a variety of
topics such as distributed systems and
technology leadership Timmo received a
bachelor's degree in computer science
from Carnegie Mellon University I'm an
MS in computer science from the
University of Wisconsin she's currently
a member of the Apache Software
Foundation and there's New York City her
husband and son hello welcome to the
show thank you for having me
our topic today is real-world
distributed systems could you started
off by briefly describing what a
distributed system is sure so my
favorite definition of distributed
system comes from Leslie Lamport he was
one of the famous you know sort of early
researchers in the field and he
describes a distributed system as a one
in which the failure of a computer you
didn't know existed can render your own
computer machine unusable so I love that
definition because I think that people
can get very hung up on distributed
systems being about there's a network in
the flow so you know oh well if you are
talking over the network to a database
you are in a distributed system for
example
so you know even when you were in like
old-school three-tier architecture land
right where you were building some kind
of a view layer and an application layer
and a database layer and if those went
over the network to talk to each other
but even if there were only like three
of them or even two of them that you
know that is technically in some ways
has some of the complexities of a
distributed system because you are going
over the network there are more failure
domains but my the reason that I like
the Lampert description where it's the
failure of a computer you didn't know
existed is that it really gets I think
to the heart of wind distributed systems
become more than just another little
thing that can fail and something where
you have so much more complexity than
it's possible for you to easily reason
about I think that's really that tipping
point right when you don't know exactly
you know you're calling systems that are
calling other systems that you don't
even know about and you know some
downstream systems failure can cause you
to be failing and you know you didn't
even know that that downstream system
maybe even existed do you think it's a
it would be a fair assessment to say
that we all are building distributed
systems all the time because by that
definition there isn't really anything
left that doesn't talk to something else
that you don't know well so I think you
know yes and no I mean look I would for
this novel writing thing not a novel
book writing thing that I did in
November I used a piece of software
called Scrivener it's a you know it's a
text editing you know made for people
writing long work so that you're writing
books or you're writing screenplays it's
made for that right if you're writing a
scriveners type program you're probably
not worried too too much about network
stuff right you're worried about writing
to disk as long as the operating system
that you're writing this thing for is
reliable then your programs gonna
install on this comparison's computer
and work and you know that's there's
less and less software like that these
days because we're all building these
cloud aware you know blah blah blah
systems
but I think there is something to be
said for don't don't worry about
problems you don't have yet and even
though there's even though you can be
building even a networked piece of
software that will have some complexity
that doesn't mean that you have to
engage with the entire world of
distributed systems complexity to build
that software to build it as well as it
needs to be built and to make it usable
so when do people have to worry about
this thing what is the tipping point
what's the threshold that you have to
cross when the simple thing where we
really don't worry that much about parts
of it being distributed turns into
something it really becomes a major
issue you need to be wary so I think
that that's a good question so I think
that the tipping point tends to come
when you when you really have many
different systems that you you or your
team or your software is is run across
so anyone who's working in a services
architecture especially a micro-services
type of architecture you're starting to
get some of that complexity doesn't mean
you're embracing all of it that you need
to be embracing all of it but you're
starting to get some of it versus for
example if you're building like a code
that runs in a web server and you happen
to run that web server horizontally
scaled so that you can have more people
accessing it but you don't necessarily
but you're not sharding your database
you're not using multiple different data
stores the distributed systems problems
that you need to be engaging with in
that horizontally scaled but maybe not
that not that complex web server you
know they're just a different scale of
distributed systems complexity so you
know it kind of comes in it'll come in a
little bit depending on what you're
doing right if you're working with a
database over the network you need to
understand the way that failures are
communicated to your client so you know
if you do a request to that database and
the network drops out how do you figure
out whether the request succeeded or
failed there's a little bit of a
distributed systems complexity there
even if you're just doing these simple
you know three-tier architecture kind of
model but you probably don't need to
worry about really really detailed you
know transaction retries and you know
storing extra state around you know
multiple different versions of the same
data because it's spread across multiple
different machines that may or may not
be in sync may or may not be able to
communicate with each other right you
know there's there's you know
distributed systems are as much an
engineering problem as they are a theory
problem and that means that you're going
to apply as much theory as you need to
solve the engineering problem but you
don't want to apply a lot more mm-hmm
so so some people say that you have a
distributed system as soon as a web
browser and there's in the picture
because the browser as a client accesses
your server while I distributed system
would you agree with that or is that an
example of something where you'd say
that
it is technically but not practically
relevant yeah yeah I mean I guess I what
I would ask is like so what's the point
what-what are we getting from from
making that statement what are we trying
to teach developers about and when you
make that statement right what are you
trying to get them to be aware of what
kinds of things do you think they should
be worrying about that they're not
worrying about normally because I think
that's a more useful thing than saying
it's a distributed system it's like yeah
okay it's a server system so what right
if it's a distributed system where you
are never caching state that you're
trying to modify within the browser then
kind of like who you know does it matter
that it's a distributed system or do you
just need to think about like oh well
don't try to you know cache a bunch of
state do a bunch of modifications on
that state in the browser and then talk
to the web server and then you know
because you could fail you could lose
all that state that you cache because
the customer closed it you know I make a
point in one of my talks I think that
people really underestimate humans
ability to have intuitive understanding
of systems that they're very deeply from
and I think that includes both
developers and users of certain types of
network software right like we all
understand that if we are typing
something in our browser window and the
browser window crashes it's likely that
we will lose that data we understand
that just because it's happened to us a
bunch of times probably we may not like
understand the reasoning behind it but
we know that that will happen because
it's happened to us in the past so we
know that it's a risk so as users we
know that it's a risk and will get
really annoyed when it happens and then
as web developers we also know that it's
a risk and we know that if we're doing
something we're losing that state
halfway through matters we're probably
going to be more actively sending it
over to the server versus well you know
whatever I'm just building some little
thing and you know if the browser
crashes the users got bigger problems I
don't care like they'll come back to me
or they won't whatever right so I just I
do think that I think that you can't
underestimate people's intuitive
understandings of the problems and the
spaces that they work in everyday and
and that sometimes we get really hung up
on the jargon of distributed systems
maybe because it sounds cool or it's
hard or complex or whatever without
thinking about yeah okay but like how is
this useful to the people who are
working every day just trying to make
good systems that their customers are
gonna want to use that you know are
gonna mostly do the right thing the
within reasonable failure domains mm-hmm
okay so let's talk about situations
where we actually have crossed that
threshold or or we are actually building
something where the fact that it's a
distributed system becomes important
what are what are some of the challenges
that people can run into and how would
you address them sure so I think that
the challenges that people tend to run
into especially when they get to these
really large scaling systems well I I so
let's back up and say why do people
build
distributed systems when you think of
the classic distributed system you're
probably thinking of like the Google
scale systems right that they that they
build and they've written a bunch of
different papers about what they do
right or maybe you're thinking of like
Facebook scale systems or you know
Twitter or whatever you could you could
think of these or Netflix is a great
example right you know you imagine these
just clusters data centers full of
computers running bunches of different
code it's all sort of working together
to create some kind of experience and so
one point that I like to make is when
you think about why these companies
built these systems why they went to
distributed systems they kind of went
for two reasons right they went because
they needed to scale because they had
problems that would not fit easily on a
single machine they had more data they
had more volume of users they had more
computation whatever or and/or they also
needed failure tolerance so they wanted
to have a really highly available 24 by
7 system where if a machine failed if
something failed the system would
survive a certain amount of failure so
the challenge is of course that scaling
and failure tolerance are making each
other harder right so as you scale you
put more machines out there you put more
Network out there you have more moving
parts you have more complexity and you
have more places for failure to happen
right and there are just like countless
post-mortems out there from big
distributed systems you know vendors
from Amazon from Netflix from whomever
where they talk about oh yeah so this
other system that we build that that
this third system relies on it had some
Network issues or it had some disk
issues and so it's sort of degrading its
performance and then the other system
kept trying to hammer it and it didn't
back off and it caused this other system
to start having problems and and thus we
had downtime basically right you see
these you know really interconnected
complex parts working together and
though they they can fail right each one
has their own independent failure
domains and it's really really really
hard to
right a system where you think about all
of the possible failures that can happen
to you and that can happen to tertiary
systems and account for all of them
nobody does that perfectly right even
the best developers the best companies
nobody does that perfectly so you've got
this massive scale which makes failure
harder okay so how do we deal with
failure the ways that we deal with
failure tend to make scaling harder
right we put a bunch of redundancy and
we write data multiple places all of a
sudden you're doing more work you've
added more overhead to make sure that
when you do fail you don't lose data or
you know you you whatever you lose less
you have or some redundant work going on
so it's less likely that you're you're
gonna fail in all of these different
ways but okay well now you've made it so
that your scaling is less efficient you
have to have more machines to scale the
same amount so you know it's these two
elements are the fundamental goal of
building these big distributed systems
what they're also fundamentally in
conflict and what you see is people
really decide on their distributed
system usually balancing those two
things they decide which of them they
care about more to some extent this is
it's almost like a slight rephrasing of
the cap theorem is one of those famous
distributed systems you know pieces of
research right which says that you
basically if you have a distributed
system you really can't get rid of the P
is partition tolerance and you have to
be able to withstand some kind of
network partition or you're not a
distributed system okay so ignoring the
P you have C of the consistency meaning
can you lose data can you have people
read the data at the same time and see
sort of different results where where
does that fall out and availability how
many degradation how many failures can
you tolerate and still serve responses
to client and so most people are sort of
twiddling between those two axes right
to make sure you know - okay well we can
show some stale data or even potentially
lose data that's better to do that than
to not have something that responds to
our clients or you know what we'd rather
if we
a majority of nodes not be available at
all because that would reduce our
ability to be you know consistent in the
way that our clients are expecting so
you're really balancing between those
two between those two things as you
decide how to really structure and
architect the distributed system that
you're building mm-hmm
it seems to be implicit in what Jesus
just said is is also a trade-off or a
axis from simplicity to complexity right
to you the things become much more
complex and so you add lots of lots of
possible things that can fail mix that
makes a little sad so as you said at the
beginning that this is what what Google
and Facebook the Netflix phase do normal
people face it as well or is it really
just only if you're building a global
scale since to normals people certainly
face it I think that normal people face
it when they build out services
architectures whether or not you call
them micro services you know I think
services architectures are a very sane
way to think about software at a certain
scale and that that scale does not have
to be Netflix scale that scale does not
have to be massive scale it does it
should probably be more than
proof-of-concept scale right like you
know it's not clear to me that you
should start writing your software in a
services architecture but once you've
proven out and gotten to the situation
where you have 30 40 50 developers there
can be a lot of value in thinking about
the entities of your system that can
operate independently and pulling those
into services and you know writing
writing a system that joins those
entities as necessary and allow sort of
independent development and independent
ownership of of data instead of a big
monolith you can do mana let me look
nothing nothing wrong
intrinsically with monoliths but I think
in the modern the way that modern
software developers tend to build
software and the kinds of
that we're solving and the increasing
sort of ease of creating a distributed
system I think you know one thing that I
want to make a point on is I think the
reason that you see so many distributed
systems today is not just because people
have the need for more scale and they
have the need for more you know failure
tolerance or what have you it's actually
that it's just easier to do it because
we have the cloud and it's easier to get
access to hardware and it's easier to
get access to network detached servers
and network attached discs and the
network and there are more you know
systems out there that are distributed
systems themselves for data storage and
data processing and so everybody's
already starting you know in this in a
way where it's very easy to build
distributed system at least from like
the hardware accessibility perspective
which was not the case ten years ago
right ten years ago pre cloud it was
very hard to get your hands on the kind
of software and the kind of networking
and frankly distributed data storage
types of systems that would make
building a application distributed
system so micro-services type
architecture that would make building
something big like that fairly
straightforward so you would see these
kinds of systems in large companies like
I work for Goldman Sachs and we
definitely had service-oriented
architectures all over that company but
they also had their own data centers
right they had a lot of hardware they
had a lot ten you know ten thousand
developers so there was a lot of
independent software being written but
at a smaller company even with hundreds
of developers you may not have done that
because the act the accessibility and
the speed in which you could spin up a
new server was not quite there before
the cloud release all the sudden made
that much easier mm-hmm so I I totally
agree with that let me let me just play
devil's advocate for a second here let's
say that I claim that the problem with
that is that it's become too easy to
build those things and people build
those things without knowing what
they're getting themselves into and all
those problems that they have because
they now have a really strongly
distributed system our problems that
they wouldn't have if they just start
they're boring all database architecture
maybe we should all stop pretending or
Google and just build simple stuff like
we did it 15 years ago do you think it's
it's well I do not actually have to say
that for a reputation I do not actually
believe that but let us say that's a
that's a very valid argument what would
you what would you what would you say to
that so I am actually more sympathetic
than you might expect to that argument
here here is my my personal take on all
things is you know I'm don't buy
complexity you don't need and so I am a
fan of if your data will will be
reasonably usable in a relational
database
you should probably and you're doing
transactions you should probably use a
relational database like if you really
care about transactional you know acid
whatever you don't want to lose data and
now I realized that even the relational
my sequels and what-have-you of the
world have failure conditions where they
can do unexpected things but they are so
much rarer and so much more well
understood by the operators out there in
the world and frankly by developers and
other people than the sort of MongoDB
Cassandra yada-yada world that you know
I actually am very much like I would not
we ran my my sequel at Rent the Runway
we were in my sequel you know as the
transactional database because that was
what was there when I joined but it's a
perfectly fine transactional database
for what we were doing maybe we would
have used Postgres if we were building
it today
I would certainly would not have used a
you know no sequel or later weight
distributed system to build that because
it's not worth reasoning about the edge
cases in when you're talking about
something where you're taking money from
people where you're taking orders or you
want to make sure you're actually gonna
be able to fulfill those orders so I am
actually very sympathetic and being
conservative where it matters now I
think the balance that you want to make
with conservatism is the following if
it's truly faster for your developers
to build things in a distributed system
way right if it's truly faster for them
to use certain types of systems for the
type of data that they're working with
the type of volume that they're working
with the type of application that
they're building then they should
probably use a distributed system even
if it has edge cases that they haven't
fully considered because I actually
think that the biggest cost to your
business is developer time developer
time is such a huge huge huge expense
and I think it goes both ways I think
sometimes we over build we build two
complex systems because we want to keep
developers entertained that's a not a
great reason to build a distributed
system is like cool points or you know
developer entertainment but if you're
building a system that you genuinely
believe will help your development team
be more productive scale better you know
be able to get more business features
out there and yeah okay you have an
outage that makes you realize like oh
crap the way we've been writing this
data into this table is not good and we
need to fix that
I I think if you take a step back and
you sort of quantify the potential for
for danger there it's probably less than
people think you know you have outages
of all sorts all the time when you're
actually running a business right you
have outages related to Hurricane sandy
flooding you know flooding half of New
York and cutting off your access to
certain servers right you have access
you have view and you have outages
because somebody at one of those big
companies like Amazon screws up their
distributed system and you didn't really
know you were relying on that right you
have outages because hackers attack you
you have outages because somebody
fat-finger or something you're going to
have failure and outages you're going
you are not going to be able to think
through every single possible edge case
and if you are deeply uncomfortable
working in a world where you can have
failure
then certainly I would say startup land
is probably not for you you may want to
you know look there are there are places
where this stuff is really like you
don't have out of just right you're
building flight control software maybe
you're building software to land a
person on Mars right you're building
certain kinds of financial system
software but for most people working in
small to midsize companies you are
always going to be balancing the cost of
building something
the cost of maintaining it over time and
the risk of failure that is just that is
just the balance that you do all the
time and so while I actually do think
they and I think you just need to make
that make that conscious calculation as
often as possible so that includes being
boring sometimes and that includes
taking something that may be a little
bit flaky but that's really easy and
intuitive for your engineers to use and
get started on and to run like MongoDB
for example right MongoDB is incredibly
easy for people to get started on and
for people to use and I think that's
actually a brilliant aspect of that
software is that they realize that the
startup cost for so many of the
distributed storage systems at the time
was really high actually I'm I'm not
even sure that they built it that way
because they were trying to compete with
other people that was just that for them
they thought felt like this was one of
the usability element of the distributed
system was a more important problem to
tackle first than the correctness and
you may say that that's horrible and
they're horrible people and how dare
they they tricked the industry and I'm
not going to argue either way on that
but I will say that I think that's an
interesting choice to have made that
they have made and that you know people
adopted it not just because they were
idiots but people adopted it because it
was easy for their teams to use it and
to get going with it and they got value
out of it and so you know you're making
that trade-off on both both to go
conservative and both to go you know
sort of experimental and as long as
you're constantly thinking about where
am I willing to take risks and where is
it Willie
where is it better for me to say you
know what like let's just favor
developer productivity and do this you
know an easy way or let's favor future
scaling of developer productivity and
put a little elbow grease into it now
that will pay off when we have 50
developers or 500 developers right so
you know at least these things are
really hard I think this seems really
hard but I think that's the kind of
trade-offs that you should be thinking
about so it seems a lot of the things
that you mentioned are related to areas
where there is not that much complexity
because the system is essentially
stateless you mentioned the web servers
just scaling horizontally so there was
the implicit assumption I guess that
these were statement stains how do how
those things change if we're talking
about the stateful part if we make that
distributive
yeah so I think state state is where
everything gets complicated certainly
and I think when it comes to state you
want to be thoughtful about the level of
consistency that you need for various
parts of your data and understand really
like you know where are you comfortable
having inconsistent State and where are
you where do you absolutely sort of need
that that consistency so you know so
here's a here's a great example from my
pipe rest job right so I said you know
we relied on my sequel to be the
transactional part of our data so you
know and we and that meant that if you
were placing an order if you were making
a reservation that would go to my sequel
and I did we did that because I really
wanted that stuff I didn't want to lose
that state right I wanted to that state
to be kept in a place that was you know
very very core to the business I mean
look at the my sequel database went down
with the business would not be able to
function right there there are core
parts of every business and so you're
gonna have some kind of system probably
that's storing some of the data of the
core parts of your business where if it
goes away for whatever reason it fails
you know the whole business or a large
parts of the business are not
to be able to work right so so when
you're building a distributed system and
you're dealing with parts that you
really care about consistent state you
definitely get a lot of complexity there
in fact you know so so I'm a fan of like
use a user relational database if you
can for that part of your state because
those systems again as I said tend to be
more well understood now you may still
have to do things like shard it widely
which makes an incredibly operationally
complex system and there are many
distributed systems aspects there right
where all of a sudden you're writing
data to different places if you want to
try to rebalance that data because one
shard is getting full how do you think
about managing that rebalancing without
taking your whole system down again
right balancing that scaling versus
failure tolerance that we talked about
earlier so you are definitely you know I
think one of them one of the important
things to think about as you're building
out a distributed system is where do you
care about coherence consistent state
you don't lose data you don't lose
rights you don't have people seeing
different state at different you know
looking at the database at the same time
and seeing different state you want to
be able to lock paces of data so that
multiple people can't update them at
once right things like that you're gonna
have state on the other hand that's what
I so I think of it as cache state right
my you know my personal my personal
feeling is you know if if it's ok if
people see slightly stale data it's okay
for it to be in a cache right and you
want to think very carefully about where
is it okay for people to see slightly
stale data where is it okay for you to
lose data because you can easily
reconstruct that data right and those
kinds of pieces of data are you can
serve them out of systems like frankly
MongoDB
Redis right you can use systems like
that so so for example at Rent the
Runway we actually used MongoDB
we use it for both data that was more
document like that made sense so our
product data right we have lots of
products you've got to update them they
have lots of metadata around them that
was all stored in Mungo that was sort of
because you know the process of
creating that product if we lost a piece
like if we lost a detail we could easily
reconstruct it it wasn't that big a deal
if it was slightly incoherent for or
inconsistent for a little while or if it
was slightly you know if you read
something and then you read you know you
read it again and you got a different
version of it because it had been
updated but you know whatever like it
just wasn't that big a deal we were
cashing it in a whole bunch of other
places anyway so there was just not as
much you know it's not like a placing an
order or if you put if you hit place
order and you place four orders or you
don't place an order at all but you
still think you did that's a really
terrible customer experience so
understanding you know understanding
where you can get away with thinking
less about consistency but where certain
kinds of scaling might make your life
easier right so again you know caching I
think is one of these layers where even
if you were building as you said the
parallel web server the horizontally
scaled web server and okay maybe it's
not doesn't have a lot of the challenges
of distributed system you probably had
memcache in there right and you probably
thought about what you put in memcache
and you know and you thought about okay
what data matters if it changes and I
need to know that change immediately and
evict it from the cache and what data
doesn't matter right what data can I put
on a CDN if I have a content delivery
network right again if I'm in if I'm
serving web sites some of my data is
going to be cached at the edge so it's
not even coming to my website right my
images things like that again that's
data where it's gonna be stale it might
change and be stale for a little while
and that can be okay so understanding
you know I do think that one of the one
of the major considerations as you find
yourself building a distributed system
because you will is actually an
extension of the nuance of the things
that you had to understand to even build
kind of a working
non distributed system which is what
data has to be fresh what data has to be
locked what data has to be you know can
only have a single writer and the
readers must always see the updated
versions of it what data can be slightly
stale what data can be really stale and
we don't care what data do we if we lose
a little bit of it it's a bummer but
it's not like you know like if I lose a
little bit of the clickstream data on my
website because I screw up you know the
analytics processing that sucks I've
lost invaluable information but I
haven't lost any orders I've just lost
sort of metadata right so so those I
think are those are some of the
complexities that developers do need to
understand you need to you need to have
a basic understanding of when do you
care about losing data and go from there
because if you don't have that
understanding of when do I care about
losing data then you cannot easily
reason about a distributed system if you
say well I never want to lose data
that's not true I don't I don't actually
believe that's true I think I think most
people in fact in most environments they
can say you know okay well if I lost
this click data if I lost the fact that
somebody faved this tweet that's not
good I'm sure Twitter cares very much
about you know not losing that but like
it's not like I lost somebody who gave
me money placing an order right there's
just we just have different different
thresholds of loss that we are willing
to tolerate and I think and I think
asking that question and then
understanding the implications of if I
use this type of system where can I lose
data right because because that's that's
the flip side of it right you will be
able to lose data you know different
types of systems will have different
ways in which you can either lose or
read stale data or you know sort of see
see old results and that's the that's a
big part of the balance that you're
making as you build yourself into a
distributed system a lot of all the
examples that you mentioned were or
consider
the actual application data right like
the order or maybe the product data
another part of the data that a
distributed system has to do is that
with is the actual configuration yeah
data and then the information about the
runtimes set of the things how do you
deal with yeah so that is definitely I
think one of the places where you
probably want it to be fairly consistent
in fact I would say you know so
obviously I spend a lot of time talking
about Apache zookeeper because I'm one
of the members of that project and that
was one of the original use cases for
the what I call consensus systems which
are systems like zookeeper chubby is the
system inside of Google that does this
that's built on paxos systems that are
built where they every update goes
through a consensus algorithm so hexose
again is the classic one zap zookeeper
atomic broadcast is the one inside of
zookeeper there's also raft which is a
new one that was developed you know in
the past few years and there's a bunch
of systems like @cd now relies on raft
and all of these systems are they have
sort of they do key value stores but key
value stores of not very much data so
the expectation is you're not storing a
ton of data inside of these systems but
you're you're using them to make sure
that if you write something and the
system says I got it everybody who can
access the system sees that update and
these are really useful for especially
for service orchestration type work and
large scale cluster management
understanding who is around and
available and giving those people
information so distributed locking is
another huge use case for these types of
systems right if you need to elect a
leader in you know in your distributed
system which is going to be managing all
the other processes of the of the
distributed system in some way right you
want to have you don't want to have a
system that can give you two different
leaders all right do you
two litres bad things happen so you use
some kind of a consensus algorithm and
you may just use a consensus external
consensus system like zookeeper to to
store the results to find the leader and
store the results of who is the leader
so that you never have that situation
where two people think they have what is
essentially a distributed lock right
where you don't ever have that kind of
situation similarly you do want to have
you know the configuration of your of
your global environment understanding
which servers are running and taking
which data that is generally a problem
like again it depends on how stateless
the servers might be right so you could
there are systems out there that use
like gossip protocols to identify
servers that are running which is
slightly different than using like a
consensus algorithm and having to
actually sort of configure unlike know
where the cluster of zookeepers is
running for example or the cluster of
@cd is running instead of doing that you
sort of like use UDP and these gossip
protocols to find other nodes on the
network and get information through them
and so that's a there are other ways to
solve these problems I'm honestly not
nearly an expert in that but I do think
that when it comes to write the
operational complexity of running a
distributed system that's where people
sometimes I agree actually get it can
get a little fast and loose with well I
don't really care that much about you
know the accuracy of my distributed LOC
I'm just gonna use the database to write
a distributed LOC and that's actually
not not a really awesome way to do
distributed locking even though I think
databases are great for transactional
actions that's a little bit different
than what you need for for distributed
locking and you know in particular like
you probably don't want to have to pull
a database to see if a lock state has
changed and these consensus systems all
we're built with the ability to notify
you of state changes in the systems
which is really useful in cases where
you want to immediately elect a new
leader if one failed so you don't have
to do manual failover so would you say
that every time you build it a really
distributed system you should use one of
those consensus feeding systems no so-so
well first of all like if you're
building a distributed database you may
very well just be needing to implement
your own
paxos or your own you know consensus
state machine internally to do that kind
of management right if you're trying to
sell someone a product you probably
don't want to make them spin up a
zookeeper or an EDD or whatever and then
spin up your system unless it's part of
a larger ecosystem
what don't some of those tools do that
anyways I mean some of the distributing
a lot of yes a lot of the metrics Africa
for example rely on totally yeah and I
think I would say that they do because
because they were working they were
built within environments where there
were already a lot of people using like
using zookeeper so like you can have a
zookeeper that supports a whole bunch of
the sort of Hadoop family products and a
single zookeeper can just be used to
support that whole family of things
because they're not writing that much
data into them and so and you know these
systems being built in environments
where they already had operators who
knew how to operate zookeeper it was
easier for them to build assuming that
there was a zookeeper operational within
the environment and not trying to build
the state machine within them rather
than building the state machine within
them because they again like Kafka came
out of LinkedIn LinkedIn built it
internally for their own usage now
they're trying to spin it out into a
real product that other people may buy
and use and so it will be interesting to
see if they maintain the dependence on
zookeeper if they decide to you know
build some of that stuff internally I
don't know where they're going to go
with that but you know again for their
audience that may be reasonable to say
you know what because so many people are
using zookeeper anyway because there are
many of them are already using Hadoop
for things they're using spark or storm
whatever I'm not excited I've never
quite sure which products require a
zookeeper and which don't these days but
you know if they've already got it you
know that's not gonna be the critical
part of our roadmap to build it
internally that being said you know if
you look at Cassandra if you look at
react you know you look at systems like
that which probably do have consensus
protocols built internally they're not
relying on you having this centralized
system but they're still using consensus
protocols and state machines in order to
do that cluster management piece that
they need to do and to do certain kinds
of transactional operations that they
want to provide now you can run a
distributed environment of
micro-services type things without
having a lot of holes wholesale cluster
orchestration if the pieces of your
system are independent so Rent the
Runway of micro services or services
whatever the hell you want to call them
there were lots of services right we had
lots of we have lots of you know servers
running lots of services but each
service was developed to be deployable
independent of the other services so you
don't need to do coordination their
configuration was always deployed with
the service it wasn't dynamically
changing so we didn't really need it for
that element and we weren't quite at the
scale where humans couldn't know where
humans couldn't sort of comprehend the
scope of the entire system for pure
operational perspectives meaning like if
you have an Operations person sort of
saying oh you know we have a problem
it's in this server over here right we
weren't racking we were sort of adding
new instances so quickly that we didn't
even know where they were and we didn't
have IP addresses for them and we had to
like dynamically discover oh yeah I
needed to auto-scale out that service so
it got you know automatically assigned
to this server over there we weren't we
didn't have that level of dynamism it
was still a distributed system it just
didn't have the level of dynamism that
required like a zookeeper or other kind
of sir
this coordinator to really be managing
it and I actually think that's that's a
good way to go so we we used load
balancers to enable us to deploy with a
no downtime right you can use a load
balancer to drain traffic off of nodes
and update them update their software
and then put them back in the pool and
drain the traffic off of the other ones
up to their software put them back in
the pool that doesn't work if you brake
backward compatibility with your API
endpoints but braking backward
compatibility is such a major event
should be considered to be a major event
and any in any architecture that you
know I am very reluctant to build to
build software that makes it easy to do
something that I actually think should
be a major event because it's so easy
for other things to break when you break
backward compatibility that it's just
generally not a good practice for normal
software development so so I don't think
you have to have a consensus system if
you have a distributed system of
manageable scale where you don't have a
lot of indoor dependence between the
various services you still have a
distributed system you still have
multiple services you still have some
complexity but you're not you know
you're not massively scaling you're not
auto trying to auto scale your cloud
you're not trying to just sort of throw
a service wherever is available at the
time and you know I sign it on IP and
tell everybody oh hey it's over here at
this IP right you know you have a little
bit more of a static environment that
grows at human scale rather than at like
machine dynamic scale that sounds like
like what a lot of the enterprise
environments where people are now
started to adopt micro services will
look like right they they will be much
more static than than and I started up
that might need to scale 100 fold in a
week or so so that predictability is
much higher and that seems much better
suited to something slightly more
aesthetic and slightly more reliable as
a result yeah exactly
very deployed in the beginning you
mentioned that you have a history with
with goldman sachs as well as with Rent
the Runway I believe I can't think
two companies that could be more
different than these two can you talk a
bit about the the differences both in
software engineering and architecture
but maybe also in in engineering really
the organizational aspects that you that
you experienced when you went from one
to the other yeah so obviously Goldman
Sachs is a huge financial institution
and a lot of what I did working there
was building big distributed systems and
so in many ways I in many ways actually
when I joined Goldman Sachs I joined in
2005 and when I joined them they
operated very much against the business
that you were supporting so I worked in
risk technology and that technology team
which was about I don't know the team
the immediate team for the product that
I worked on was about 60 60 to 80 people
let's say and then the wire team was
much larger than that but we were very
much dedicated to the risk management
side of the firm why technology
organization and so we were actually in
many ways able to act fairly
independently the you know and that was
somewhat startup like I mean it was very
enterprise in that you know I had to
have dressed up to go to work didn't
have to wear a suit but you know and
obviously we had all of this support
around us you know we didn't have to
rack her own hardware exactly although
we did do what I would call much closer
to DevOps than most people I think may
have imagined right we certainly
supported our own software in production
and deployed it ourselves we did not
have an ops team that did all support
and deployment we did have you know DBAs
supporting the database but we very much
as developers of the software were also
supporting it and so I think there were
actually a lot of things about those
early experiences that were very similar
to being in a start-up right you're very
close to the business your focus is
building something that will be valuable
for that business you're not trying to
you know you're not what
moving that slowly we had some freedom
of choice about what kinds of software
we use not perfect freedom but we
certainly you know so so it was it was
not as different as working at a
start-up as you might expect but it was
you know but then I worked in firmware I
worked in sorry technology
infrastructure which was much more like
big company right we were the big
centralized infrastructure team for the
entire company which meant that you know
everybody wanted to have a say in what
we worked on and you know our software
could be used by lots and lots and lots
and lots of teams but on the flip side
you know we had much less and some of
those much less freedom because we had
to get so much political buy-in for
everything we did so that was actually
what sort of drove me to leave a little
bit as I just I felt like I loved in
many ways I loved the company I had a
very good experience
you know goldman sachs is not as as evil
as people might want to believe
certainly not in the technology area
they're still they're still engineers
you know so and i got to work on some
really large-scale problems that were
much much much larger scale than most
people at startups will ever get to
experience you know and they had much
harder requirements than most startups
how did you so I did have a lot higher
threshold for you know the risk
management that I had to do the system
that I had the last system that I built
at Goldman Sachs was actually a global
service discovery system so I had to
think about how to build this
distributed system that would be
available in Asia in you know the EU in
the Americas and if part of it went down
I didn't want the whole system to go
down right that would be very bad it
would be very bad if I built a system
where if for whatever reason you know
the the Asia region was having technical
problems and America couldn't get work
done that would be really really really
bad so
you know you had to think much much
really large-scale and you know the
amount of money that you were supporting
and the amount of risk that you were
taking on if you broke something was
really high
now startup land had some similarities
in that I think you know the things that
I learned at Goldman about really
understanding and caring about the
business that I was building and working
fast getting stuff done shipping
frequently were things that I took to
rent the runway but I would say you know
the difference is of course that it's a
start-up you have to do everything
yourself
so you know you're you really have much
less support from those secret areas
that you didn't even think about when
you were working for a big company you
know we were running on cloud cloud
hardware cloud networks much less
reliable than hardware
you know supported by dedicated teams
inside of goldman sachs where you really
like owned all the servers yourself and
not still not you know that wasn't a
perfectly reliable world but it was it
was just more stable it didn't change as
much and the cloud world you know we had
a lot more problems there so learning
about that kind of failure was really
interesting and then of course learning
about just the stress and failure of
growing a team and what kinds of things
that you know didn't work an enterprise
that were really necessary in a start-up
and it was some things that surprised me
I had actually never worked in an
environment goldman sachs did not
necessarily have a lot of teams where
every single piece of software required
code review which may seem surprising
but it was the case it's not that we
never did code review and they may very
well have that requirement now but when
I when I worked there we did actually a
lot of pairing so we had a lot of pair
programming and required a lot of you
wrote a lot of tests so instead of have
reliably on code review there was a lot
more reliance on sort of the process
around building software and validation
and so I was very reluctant to require
code review and Rent the Runway and my
engineers at some point just kind of
revolted and they were like
the thing that's not working here is
that we're not doing code reviews and I
was like really okay well that's an easy
one to fix now we have to do code
reviews and so you know it's I think
sometimes there's non-intuitive things
that are actually harder and easier
depending on the size of the company and
the type of the company that people
don't really expect very interesting is
this something you would take back from
it from the lessons you learned in the
startup world if you were to work for a
big company you go oh man yeah I mean I
think what I would take back is I think
that I think even at big companies like
Goldman was good but only in places
people really get so far away from the
business and the people that they're
supporting that they they lose their
sense of what is important what is
valuable
what needs to happen and and you see
that you know you see that frankly
people feel alienated at big companies
because they don't understand why
they're building what they're building
they don't understand who they're
helping with the software that they're
building and you it's very hard at a
start-up to get away from your customer
you know it frankly I mean it rent the
runway we actually let all the employees
rent for free
so you know the male employees would
rent for their female friends or their
girlfriends or their wives and obviously
the female employees we would rent for
ourselves and so we all really got the
experience of you know being the
customer using the software as a
customer would use it we had a big
warehouse where we did a lot of
logistics and we made everybody work a
day in the warehouse and the peep this
team that built the software for the
warehouse went there very frequently and
observed the processes and you know
actually did some of the work to
understand the way the software they
were building impacted that team and I
think you know that is just such an
important everybody like pays a lot of
lip service to this I think in start-up
land and in big company land but it's
actually it's easy to lose sight of how
important it is that people be thinking
about and reminded of why they're
building what they're building who
they're helping
you know what matters to that person and
what doesn't matter to that person
mm-hmm awesome people or at the end of
our of our time are there any last words
you want to add some places you want to
point people to will have show notes of
course but maybe one particular thing
whatever yeah well I mean look if you if
you like listening to me talk I have
many many talks that I've given that are
online that you can see I I suppose what
I would point people to you know just to
like take a step back from the this
general topic of distributed systems I
hope that what everyone took away from
my conversation was you know you are in
a distributed world and you are gonna
need to think about that I don't want to
downplay that as as a fact of life right
now but that doesn't mean you have to
tackle every single problem that doesn't
mean that you have to expect that every
system is going to be you know perfectly
reliable and if it's not you know if
Kyle does a DEP some tests on it and
reveals a weakness that therefore that
system is garbage and you shouldn't use
it you know these we make a lot of
trade-offs as engineers we always have
now we just make them at larger scale
you know and sometimes those trade-offs
cause us sleepless nights and you know
and a lot of challenges but you are
always gonna be making trade-offs no
matter what you do so try not to try not
to tackle every problem tackle the
problems that you really need to solve
and kind of work on developing a sense
of what where value lies in your
business where value lies in your
software and your infrastructure where
it's reasonable to take risks and where
it's not reasonable to take risks and
just developing those instincts I think
will make the process of living in a
distributed world building distributed
systems much much easier awesome good oh
thank you so much for being with
software engineering radio and closeness
thank you for listening
thank you thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by I Triple E software magazine for
more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website @ SC - radioman to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on itunes mention a message us on
twitter at SC radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
LinkedIn Google+ or Facebook you can
also email us at team at SES radio net
this and all other episodes of SU radio
is licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
you